Hey there, and welcome to the Learn UI
Design lesson on an introduction to Figma.
So in this lesson, we're going to be
talking about all of the most basic
functionality in Figma, the 80 -20, so to speak.
It's like maybe 20 % of Figma's total
functionality, and yet 80 % of the time
that you're designing, 80 % of the things
that I do in this video course are all
covered in this lesson.
So to those ends, make sure that you can
follow along.
If you're using Figma, follow along in Figma.
and we're going to be doing a sample
project, so you can just make the sample
project with me.
If you're following along in a different
app, that's totally fine, just make sure
that you can make this sample app just
the same and you're going to be golden.
So again, this is not everything, it's
just sort of the basics and
if you're already really proficient with
Figma or your design app of choice, feel
free to skip this video entirely or at
the very least, take a look at the topics
below, make sure you can do those and
then you're good to go.
So without any further ado, let's dive in
and create our sample mobile lock screen.
All right, so now I'm on a new Figma file
on a blank page.
I've got this gray canvas that you can't
see right now, but it scrolls infinitely
in all directions.
And I'm going to start putting stuff on it.
Many times, one of the first things
you're going to put on it is a frame.
And a frame is simply what contains your design.
So if I want to make a phone design, I
want a frame that is the size of a phone screen.
To make a frame, I can go up to this menu
right here and you'll notice it has a
hotkey associated with it, helpfully
listed for us, that's F.
Now in this entire course, I use hotkeys
all the time.
And in the beginning of the course, I'll
be careful to narrate them as much as
possible so that you can start to learn
them and use them right from the get -go.
Because designing fast will allow you to
experiment with much less effort.
So F or A, frame or artboard, those terms
are synonymous.
It's going to bring up this menu here and
then I can select phone and choose
whatever phone size you have.
I have the old iPhone 13 mini, I like the
smaller screen size, but I'm going to
bring that one up in this file.
And by the way, the reason I say to
choose your own phone size is because at
the end of this, we're going to use the
Figma app and bring up the design on our
phone, because it's a weird reality of
designing for phones, but how it appears
on your laptop or your desktop can be
really different from how it appears when
it's actually on your device.
The zooming, I can control with perfect
accuracy via this menu, but to be honest,
there's really only two zooms that I use
very regularly.
And that is, if I'm scrolling around and
doing whatever in my design file, and I
decide I want to look at this phone
screen, I press Shift -2 to zoom to the selection.
So you can tell I have this selected
because it has the blue outline and then
shift zero to make the selection 100 % to
bring it to its actual full size.
Now my idea for this lesson is in order
to introduce you to all the stuff that I
commonly do in Figma in this course,
we're going to work on a sample project
and it'll be a phone lock screen, But
it'll be a phone lock screen that tries
to kind of show you your to -do list and
just make sure that you have an
intentional mindset when you open up your phone.
So the first thing I'm going to do is set
a background color for this frame.
To do that, a background color is, in
Figma, a fill.
And so if I go here, I can choose from my
personal colors.
I'm just going to choose this sort of
default -looking blue.
And that's good enough for now.
We'll kind of fiddle with it a bit later.
I'm going to add in some text that says,
What are you here to accomplish today?
And to add in text, I can select it from
the text menu up here, or handy shortcut
key, letter T.
And you'll find that basically 100 % of
the time, that's what I'm doing.
So I click and drag to define how big I
want my text box to be, and then I can
add the text.
What are you here to accomplish today?
If I press command enter, it kind of sets
the text box and I can click away to
deselect it.
This is what my design looks like so far.
I'm actually going to give this a
different font.
I'm going to change it to a font called
Babus Neue.
And there is a version of Babus Neue
that's on Google Fonts and therefore will
be included with Figma.
But if you want the full version that has
all the weights from thin to bold, you
have to go get that separately.
the link is below, and to use it, you'll
need to download the desktop Figma app.
So, that's one of the few differences
between using it in your web browser and
actually downloading the app.
Now, I'm going to change the font size,
and I can either type in a number
directly, or I can use the up arrow key
to make it bigger, or even the shift up
arrow key to make it bigger in increments
of 10.
And I'll just make it so it fits on one
line or two lines here, something like that.
Maybe I can even add in a little bit more
styling by making the word accomplished bold.
And Command -B is just the typical
shortcut for doing that.
Now designers care a lot about spacing,
and so to figure out what your spacing
is, you can hold down the Option key.
If I hold down Option and I have a layer
selected, anything else I hover on, it's
going to show me the spacing between how
those layers line up.
So you can see, I have 34 pixels on one
side of this and 27 on the other.
And since we're designers, we want it to
be even.
We want it to be exactly the same on both sides.
And that is a handy case for rulers.
So if I press Shift -R, I bring up my
rulers, and Shift -R will make them
invisible, and it will also make them
visible again.
I'm going to bring in a ruler and make
it, let's say, 32 pixels from the left
-hand side, and then I'm going to do one
32 pixels from the right -hand side as well.
And the reason I go with that value is
because the default margin on iPhone is
actually 16 pixels, so just doubling that
will give this kind of a indented appearance
where it seems sort of noticeable.
Now, the width of my frame here is 375,
so I'm just going to do some math real
quick, 375 minus 32, 343, and it's kind
of snapping to the edge of this textbox,
which is messing with where I want this
ruler to go
,
but
there we go, now it's at 343.
So now when I bring my textbox back
there, I can align it perfectly here, and
then I'll just change the size to make
sure this stays on two lines.
By the way, the size does not have to be
an integer.
I could say 44 .5 if I wanted to.
Now of course, if I kind of want to
evaluate the design as a whole, I can do
my Shift -2, Shift -0 business and zoom
out and see what things look like.
So, so far, so good.
Maybe I'll move this text down just a
little bit.
And I'm using shift and the down arrow
key to move it down 10 pixels at a time.
The only other thing I'm going to adjust
right now is I notice that my text box is
set to a fixed size because I clicked and
dragged it and it just made the text box
the size of what I clicked and dragged.
But I actually want to use this mode,
which I think is much more common, auto -height.
And now the text box will resize based on
however much text is in it.
So it'll get taller if there's more text
and less tall if there's less.
We have this headline that greets us when
we open our phone.
What are you here to accomplish today?
And just for way of example, I'll put in
a couple little to -do list items.
I'm gonna press Shift -R to see my ruler.
And I'm just gonna, I pressed T, but if I
just click, it'll start a text box right there.
So I could do something like Call Alice.
But I really don't want this to be as big
as the header text.
I actually want it to be more like a
normal text size.
And on iPhone, we'll cover this more in
the sizing lesson, but on iPhone, I
happen to know that 17 is the default
font size, at least for their default font.
So I'm going to do that.
And I'm also going to choose a font
called Input Sans Narrow.
You can use this one, there's links on it
below, but it is $5 per weight to download.
And so you could also use the free font
JetBrains mono if you're looking for
something kind of similar.
So now callAlice is my first item.
And what I'm going to do is I'm actually
going to hold option and click and drag
to create a duplicate of the layer.
Now, I want this to be the second to do
item in the list.
So I'm going to hold shift and that will
keep it perfectly horizontally aligned
with the element that I duplicated it from.
And so call Alice can now be email Bob or
something like that.
And then I can do the same thing again, right?
Holding shift and option while clicking
and dragging.
And then I let Figma hopefully put the
spacing between these at the exact same amount.
And by the way, if you do that and then
you press command D, it'll just create
more layers, more duplicate layers at
exactly the same spacing that you were doing.
So that can be a quick way to create a
little list of elements.
Now I'm starting to get a sense of what
this to -do list will look like.
I'm also going to put in the date and
time at the top of the screen.
And to do that, I'm again going to create
a duplicate of the text layer that I
already have.
And we'll talk about this much more in
the course, but I prefer to duplicate
existing layers because it means I end up
with fewer text styles as I'm sort of
exploring what styles to use, and that
will make things look neater.
So I'll have 9 41 AM right there.
And then by holding option shift, I can
click and drag a duplicate layer and
constrain it to be the same place vertically.
And let's put in a date here, Monday,
January 1st.
Of course, now it becomes really clear
that it loses alignment with the right
hand ruler, and so what I want to do is
actually make the text aligned right.
And then I hold shift while clicking and
dragging to keep it constrained along
this axis and there.
Now, even if it's Monday, January 17th,
it'll still stay aligned just as it should.
Now, I'm going to press shift R to hide
my rulers and then select the artboard
and do shift 2, shift 0.
So here's the design as it stands so far.
One thing I want to call your attention
to is that every single element that
we've put on this page exists in this
list that's been building out on the
layer list on the left side, on the left
-hand side here.
One thing I want to call your attention
to is every element that we've put on the
page so far also exists as a layer in
this layers list on the left -hand side.
And overall, a great way to think about
Figma as with many other design apps is
that your layers are on the left, your
styling is on the right.
That's a fairly typical pattern here.
Now with the layers list, the only thing
I want to say right now is the order matters.
So if I do something like press, let's
say, R to create a rectangle, I can go in
here and create it, or I can just press R
and I can click and drag a rectangle.
If that rectangle is at the top of the
layers list, it appears on top of all the
things that are below it.
And if it's at the bottom, which I can
move it just by clicking and dragging,
the reverse is true.
Now it's below all of these other
elements that we've already added in.
So, to move something with a hotkey, I
can say command close bracket will make
it go up one layer, and command open
bracket makes it go down a layer.
And then by holding down option while
pressing either of those command option
closed bracket, moves it to the top and
command option open bracket moves it to
the very bottom.
So those will be things that I will use
fairly frequently.
While we're on the subject, you'll notice
that when I hover over a layer, I also
have the ability to lock it.
And so when it's locked, it just means it
can't be selected.
If I draw a little selection rectangle,
it'll select every layer that my
selection rectangle touches except for
locked layers, so that's what happened there.
And I can lock with command shift L,
excuse me, that unlocks it as well as
locks it, so it just basically toggles
that status.
And then of course, I can also hide it
and unhide it, which is exactly what it
seems like.
So both of those things will be useful in
a variety of cases.
And the hotkey for hiding is Command
-Shift -H, both to hide it and to make it visible.
So I'm going to delete this layer, now
it's selected, but if I just press
Delete, I will remove it from the design entirely.
Alright, now let's do a little bit more
visual styling on this.
Let's just make things appear a little
more interesting.
So if I select my overall frame, which I
can do either from the canvas or from the
layer list, I'm going to go to my fill,
I'm going to open it up and I'm actually,
instead of doing a solid color fill, I'm
going to switch over to a gradient.
So now I'm at a gradient and a gradient
is just a sort of a smooth transition
between one color and another one.
If I click on the second color, I could
choose something totally different.
I mean, I could set it manually here or
just to keep things simple, I will select
this color right here.
And gradients are cool because in
addition to changing the colors, I can
also change the direction of them.
So I'll just change this gradient from
top left to bottom right, which adds a
little more kind of pizzazz to things.
And as always, I'm like, Shift -2, Shift
-0, kind of see this thing at 100 % and
evaluate how I feel about this.
The next thing I'm going to do is I'm
going to give some visual distinction to
each of the elements in the to -do list.
And I know that on mobile, specifically
on iPhone, every tappable element should
be at least 44 pixels by 44 pixels.
So I'm going to draw a rectangle by
pressing R and I'm going to make it 44
pixels tall and I'm going to make it the
full width of the screen.
Now, I can adjust the height when I have
an element selected by pressing command
up and down.
That will adjust the bottom and then I
can adjust the left edge.
I can adjust the right edge with command
left arrow and command right arrow.
And I can hold shift to adjust by 10.
So, that is one way to adjust the size of things.
Of course, I can also adjust the width
and the height as well as the x value and
the y value directly on the property pane here.
Now, I want this rectangle to actually be
below the text layer, so I will just
press command open bracket a couple times
until it is below all of the to -do list items.
And then I can use the up arrow and down
arrow to get it so that the text appears
vertically centered within the rectangle
around it.
And remember, by holding option, I can
see, you know, these measurements can be
useful to see, that it's 16 on the top
and 16 on the bottom, but it's not always
the case that what appears centered is
actually numerically centered, and that's
an important thing to remember.
If there is 16 pixels between the text
box and the rectangle, then that means
the distance between each of these items
needs to be double that, or 32 pixels.
When you select multiple items and they
all have the same spacing, Figma
helpfully lets you edit it directly here.
So I can just go type 32 and it'll adjust everything.
On Canvas, this control, you can get it
to pop up, but I really rarely do this,
to be honest.
Now, I can hold option and shift to
create a second layer here and I can
duplicate it with command D a couple
times and get these all in the right place.
Now, we don't want the boxes to be the
shade of gray because it makes things
impossible to read and it's terrible.
What color do we want it to do?
Well, I kind of have this fun idea where
we're gonna make it white, but we're
gonna make it a translucent white so that
you can kind of see through the box to
different degrees.
Here's what I mean.
First task, let's make it white.
That's as easy as coming to the fill
color and clicking over here.
Okay, first task, let's make these layers white.
There's actually a bunch of ways to do that.
One is by going to the fill and then
opening up the color picker and just
sliding to white.
Yeah, technically, this makes the text
invisible, but we'll fix that in a sec.
I can, you know, also open...
I can also type the value, the hex value
for white in right here, which is
FFFFFFF, or because it's all the same
letter in the hex value, just F and press enter.
that'll make it white and I can also use
a hotkey like options, like control C,
which brings up the little color picker
tool and if I just click on anything else
white in my design, now, that's white as well.
I is another hotkey that works for that.
So many ways to make things white.
Oh, here's one more.
You can just type white in here and that
will also work.
But I said we kind of want to do an
interesting visual effect where these are
each slightly different opacities.
So to change opacity, I can go over to
layer and the percentage value that's
next to it is the opacity of the layer.
I can type in something directly or use
the arrow, the down arrow or the shift
down arrow or shift up arrow to adjust
the value by increments of 10.
Another way, and this is what I do
through most of the course, is to just
press a number, 1, 2, 3, all the way up
to 0, and it will switch to that opacity,
but times 10.
So pressing 2 goes 20%, pressing 3 gives
30%, pressing 0 gives 100%, so that means
to do 0 % opacity, I actually have to
press 0 twice in rapid succession.
Now, that's not what I want though.
I want 40%, so I'm going to press 4, and
now I have 10%, 20, 30, 40, and it it
kind of has this interesting scale effect.
Now we'll be talking a lot more about
this soon, but one thing I frequently do
is use Command D to duplicate a frame or
an artboard and then try out something
slightly different.
So in this case, I'm also going to try
out changing what's called the blend mode.
And we go over these a lot more in the
photography and imagery lesson, but I can
use a blend mode like overlay or soft
light to just give a little bit more
effect to things.
So I kind of like soft light right here,
but I can actually now raise the opacity.
So, I can now raise the opacity to make
the effect a little more visible.
So maybe this will become 25, which I
just press 25 in rapid succession.
For 50, I just press 5.
For 75, I have to actually type out the number.
And then for 100%, I just type 0.
And I can say, which of these do I like better?
To me, it's a little bit of a wash, but
the blend modes is kind of an interesting
one, so maybe we'll go with that.
Now, technically, this is a to -do list,
which means that each of these things
should be kind of an item that you can
check off the list.
And when I think of checking something
off, I feel like we're going to want to
display a little checkbox to the left of
each piece of text.
So, I'm going to use shift -clicking to
get all these layers at once, and then
I'm going to use shift -clicking and
dragging to move them over here to put a
little space, or give a little space for
our checkboxes.
Now, I'm pressing Shift -R so I can see
where the ruler is.
Remember, everything is gonna be aligned.
And then, I'm gonna press R to make a
rectangle, and I'm gonna make it just a
little bit bigger than the text itself,
maybe something like 20 by 20 pixels.
That should be fine.
Now, one fun thing in Figma is you can
press Shift -X, and that changes what was
a fill, or a background fill, into a
stroke, which is kind of like a border or
an outline.
So, Shift -X again, this little gray is
back as my fill, Shift -X, now it's my stroke.
Shift -X, Fill, Shift -X, Stroke.
Now, I can also do things like change the
border radius a little bit, and I'm just
gonna change the border radius so that it
feels like it matches the font.
you'll notice the font feels kind of a
little bit rounded, right?
So maybe I'll make it 40 pixels from the
left here.
The font feels a little bit rounded.
I kind of want this to feel the same way.
I can also change the width of the stroke.
So maybe 1 .5 here
.
That feels pretty consistent with the text.
Of course, the color is different.
So what I'm gonna do is just use command
C and grab that white color very easily.
And then I can do option, shift, click
and drag, get that position and press
command D twice to get these exactly
where I want them.
Now you can probably already tell, but
now I want to view the design at 100 %
and just kind of evaluate how we're doing.
To quickly skip from selecting a child
layer to selecting the parent layer,
which in this case is this frame right
here, just press shift enter.
So now I have the frame selected and I
can do Shift -2, Shift -0, and there we go.
And maybe I remove the rulers with Shift
-R. Hey, this isn't looking so bad.
Now that I'm evaluating it, uh, I'm
really quickly thinking, I'm actually
going to change the opacity to 80, 60,
40, and 20, just to make these a little
bit darker.
And this is something you'll hear me say
so much.
We always reserve the right to change our mind.
Like until this thing is shipped and
live, I mean, even then, I guess you
could technically change your mind.
It's just a little more annoying.
But as designers, in this early stage,
we're exploring, and just because you
have something on the canvas does not
mean you're committed to it.
Sometimes you have to do it just to see
how it's going to look.
Okay, so I like this a little bit better,
but now let's see what would happen if
one of these items was done, right?
Like, I'm kind of imagining this would be
struck through, and there would be a
little check mark in the checkbox,
And maybe we'd even reduce the opacity of
this text, so it just kind of feels
lighter and like, not quite disabled, but
just not as clickable.
So a lot of my basic text styling is
right here, but if I want more advanced
text styling, I can click the little
three dot menu here and then under
decoration, I can go to strikethrough, so
that's pretty easy.
To change the opacity, it's like I said,
we just press 8 to say 80%, do the same
thing with this little checkbox, 8 for 80%.
And already it looks a little bit more
subtle, that's kind of cool.
Drawing a checkmark in the checkbox is a
bit more complicated, though.
So I'm going to zoom way in, and then
we're going to use a new tool, the Pen tool.
So, this is it right here, but you'll see
the hotkey is P, and that's what I used
throughout this course.
So what I'm going to do is just click
somewhere and that's going to start
drawing a pen.
And that's going to start the drawing.
And basically, I could just click on a
whole bunch of points wherever I want to.
And it'll just put points in.
And so, this actually looks okay already.
If I press enter, it sort of completes it.
And I have the ability to change, you
know, do I want square or round?
And if you open up the advanced options,
then you can say, should the join, that
is kind of the elbow here, should it have
like a right angle and be sort of
geometric or should be a little more rounded.
Well, since we went with this round
corner here and our font in some sense
feels a little bit more rounded and
friendly, that's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to try and be consistent in
that sort of stylistic way.
So I'm just going to adjust the sizing
and kind of get it where I think it belongs.
and then press eight so that it's
consistent in terms of opacity with all
the other elements in the checked, on the
checked to do item.
So command zero or shift zero brings me
out to a hundred percent again, so far,
so good.
Now looking at this design, we've
actually gotten pretty far with text and
rectangles, but design is not just text
and rectangles, there are circles too.
So I'm gonna press O is for oval, I
guess, and I can click and drag an oval.
I don't want any of these other crazy
shapes, though.
I want a perfect circle.
To get a perfect circle, hold shift, okay?
And I'm going to hold shift until my
circle is about yay big and I'm going to
drag it to the bottom of the screen.
So it's technically kind of off screen
and I'm gonna try and get it totally centered.
I'm gonna get it centered so that the
circle is bisected by the bottom of the
screen, and it's also horizontally aligned.
By the way, Figma tries to be helpful and
get things to be aligned smart, but if
you feel like something is not quite
aligned, you can center something
horizontally with this little button
here, or, Command -Z to undo, I can press
Option -H, and that will do the same thing.
So, there are a bunch of ways of
horizontally centering something.
Option V does it for vertical centering,
and of course, I can use these buttons up
here too.
Now, if I want to resize this circle, all
of a sudden, I have this issue where I
want it to stay a circle, but I also want
it to stay centered, and I want to resize
from the center of the circle.
So Option is what I need to hold.
I hold Shift in order to keep it a
perfect circle, and I hold Option to
resize it from exactly the center.
Now, before I can tell the size, though,
I need to put the elements on it that I
intend to.
And actually, boy, I'm full of ideas.
Before I do that, we're going to make
this white.
And maybe like 10 % opacity.
That's too light.
How about 30?
That's a little bit better.
And we're just going to put some text on it.
And the text is going to say slide up to unlock.
Okay, oops, look at that.
I tried to select the text and I
accidentally selected the circle because
the circle is at the very top.
So I can select it and then use my hotkey
to move it to the bottom.
Now I can say slide up to unlock, but we
have all sorts of issues.
What we really want is for this text to
be centered, so I can do that.
But then I also want to center it in the
screen, so I'm gonna do that with option H.
And then I also want it to be on two lines.
I don't want it to be this wide.
So normally if I start to resize, it
moves just the right edge, which of
course removes the centering.
But by holding option, I can resize from
the center.
And there we go.
That looks good.
I'll use kind of up arrow there.
Slide up to unlock.
What could be clearer?
And that's done through this effects
section on the property panel.
So if I click plus, I can choose from
these four effects, at least for right now.
And drop shadow is just sort of like your
typical shadow.
I can adjust the X value and Y value,
which is where the shadow appears, as
well as the blur, which is kind of how
big it appears.
So it might be a little bit difficult to
see, but I can always toggle the visibility.
Oh yeah, that's very difficult to see.
try increasing the opacity of it and then
I can toggle the visibility and you can
see it's subtle but it's there.
Anyhow, we'll cover this a whole lot more
in the lighting and shadows lesson but I
figured we'd just do it because it does
come up plenty throughout the rest of the
course as well and I'm just gonna make
this fairly subtle.
Now the only other thing I want to do
here is maybe draw a little up arrow just
so it's doubly clear that you're supposed
to drag this thing up, so I'm going to go
back to my pen tool, just like I used to
draw the checkmark.
I press P, and then I draw one point.
Again, it tries to helpfully make it easy
for me to draw a vertical line.
I can also hold shift just to be sure.
I'm going to start drawing my line there.
And you're going to notice that when you
zoom in enough, you actually see where
each individual pixel is, and that this
is not on the pixel lines exactly.
And if you press Ctrl -P, it'll switch
into what's called Pixel Preview, and you
can toggle back and forth between the
vector version, which zooms in infinitely
far, and the pixel version, which kind of
shows things pixelated.
Now, this is an iPhone, so technically it
has very high resolution.
I shouldn't need to worry about this a
tremendous amount,
But it's not the worst habit to try and
make sure that your vectors that you
draw, any sort of line or shapes that
you're drawing, tend to line up with the
pixels themselves.
So if I do that, you can see that there's
much less blurring of this line across
pixels, which is called aliasing.
Now, I press Enter to go back into Edit
mode, and I'm going to select here.
You'll see I'm not drawing a point, so if
you ever have a point selected and you're
not drawing one, It means you just need
to press P again, and I'm going to hold
shift to get a nice 45 degree angle.
And this is what's going to help me draw
my arrow.
Now I don't actually want to continue
drawing from this point.
I want to draw from here, whoops, click
back on that point.
And now Figma has this helpful feature
called vector networks, where I don't
need to just draw like one shape where
every point is connected to only two
other points.
Instead, this point is connected to three.
And if you know anything about drawing
vector shapes, that's a little bit unique
to Figma.
It's kind of nice, though.
Now, let's see how this looks.
I zoom out, and of course, I want to
press Option H to horizontally center that.
And I would say this actually looks a
little bit too thick.
Now, I have a couple ways of dealing with
that, and we'll talk about this plenty
throughout the course.
The most obvious way is to make it
thinner, but I can also reduce the
opacity, which is sort of a different
version of making something blend in.
So maybe it's at 80 % or whatever, if I
go to command zero, now it feels like the
arrow, even though it's a little bit
thicker than the text, kind of balances
out with the text, because even though
it's thicker, it also has a lower opacity.
Pretty cool.
We've already covered so many of the main
tools that you're going to use, but
probably the most common one that we
haven't talked about yet is the line
tool, which is right here.
And if I'm just looking for where I'm
going to put a line, let me press shift R
so I can see my rulers, I'm just going to
draw a little underline and it's going to
go from ruler to ruler.
Look at how much stuff is aligned here.
So much stuff is either centered or
aligned with these rulers.
And now I can give this a pretty low
opacity, maybe something like 30%, maybe
a little bit more, 50.
I don't know.
I feel like that's not so bad.
Now if I did want to move stuff around, I
could always select these three layers
and then kind of move them.
Or one handy thing I can do is press
Command G, and that takes all the layers
I've selected and puts them into a group.
The nice thing about groups is you can
move them as a group.
The less nice thing about groups is if
you ever try and resize it, you get this stuff.
Where your text gets all messed up.
Whenever that happens, it means you
actually don't want to use a group.
You want to use a frame, and you want to
use constraints.
Let's talk about what that means real quick.
So just as Command -G, turn these things
into a group, Shift -Command -G ungroups them.
And I'm going to use a special type of
group called a frame, just the same sort
of frame as surrounds this, except it's
not going to be a whole separate design,
it's going to be a frame that just has
our little status bar right here.
And to create a frame, I can go right
here and select this, and then draw it on
and put these things in.
Or what I think is often the easier way
to do it is just press Option -Command -G.
So now these three elements are in their
own frame.
And one thing I can do when something is
in a frame is I can tell it constraints
for how it should act when there is resizing.
So I actually want this January 1st to be
anchored to the right hand side so that
if this resizes, this frame resizes, this
will always stay anchored to the left and
then this will always stay anchored to
the right.
and then this line, I actually want to go
from left to right.
So now if my frame resizes, you'll see
that the line, the little underline below
always goes from the very left to the
very right and the Monday, January 1st
always stays anchored at the very right.
Now, one thing that's very likely to
happen as you are designing and showing
people your designs and creating new
screens is you have elements that you
want to stay in sync with each other.
And if you make a change in one screen,
and you don't want to have to go change
it in a million places
.
In fact, we could even see that within
the screen for a to -do item.
Like, for instance, if we decide that we
actually want the checkbox to be a little
bit bigger, then it would be annoying to
have to go and update all four of these.
Or if we want the text to be a little bit
more to the right, it would be annoying
to go update all four of these.
So Figma very helpfully provides a way
for us to do this, and it's called components.
So to create a component, I'm just going
to duplicate all these layers at once and
bring them down here.
And then I'm going to make a component
out of them, which I can do here, or you
can see the hotkey option command K.
That's like what I'm doing all the time.
Now, this component, you'll notice, this
is actually the parent component.
It's sort of like the master that all the
little children components pay attention to.
So it has four diamonds.
They're filled in.
Again, that means it's the parent.
We'll get to that in a sec.
I'm going to rename it using command -R
and I'm just going to say to do item.
Now when I press option and click and
drag and with a shift, and I create a
second component, I'll put a little space
between them here actually so we can see them.
Now what I can do is update just the
parent and the child updates instantaneously.
And this would happen even if this
component was on a different page, on a
different frame, even in a different file.
It's worth pointing out, though, that
updating the parent does update the children.
Updating the child does not update the parent.
So if I say call Bob, just that child
stays how it is.
It's only when I update the parent that
things start getting updated everywhere.
So creating this component is nice
because now these three can stay in sync,
but I actually have a different styling
here for this fourth item, because it's
already done.
And so what I'm going to do is actually
create a different state of the component.
And this is where things get a little bit fancier.
I'm going to drag my component off to the
side of the screen here, because now I'm
treating this component as something
where the parent version is in its own
special place, and on the designs
themselves will only be child versions.
So I'm going to create what's called a
variant of this component, which means
it's going to have some styling changes.
It's going to be the styling changes that
allow us to have this text crossed off
and a lower opacity here.
And then Figma will allow us to very
easily say which of the two component
variants we want to use throughout.
So if I go here, I need to go to
properties and add one.
I'm going to add a variant.
You don't need to worry about the other
ones right now.
And so I'd say the property will be
called a complete and there's really two
States that it might be in false and true.
So I've got one variant here.
I'm going to press plus, which makes the
second one and complete.
I'm going to type true, and then I'm
going to go make the styling changes here
that show that this thing is complete,
which for now was 80 % opacity and with
this text making it struck through.
Now what I can do is whenever I have a
component here, a child component, I
create a new version and I see this
property right here that says complete
and whenever I say yes, it changes the
styling to match.
And again, if I change these two in any
way, it'll update right here.
Now, the only other thing I need to do to
finish this up is add in a layer to my
component, this, and it has 80 % and it
appears here.
So everything is perfect.
Now, I'll just spiff this up real quick.
Now, I want to spiff this up real quick,
but I'm kind of running into this issue,
which is I need to move this one down
some amount, and I need to put in two in
between them, so that there's the call
Alice and gift for Carol.
So because I want to work with these
items as a list that always has
consistent spacing, I'm going to use a
Figma feature called auto complete.
I'm going to use a Figma feature called
auto layout.
So to create an auto layout, just select
multiple items and you have this auto
layout thing right here.
I can press plus, the hotkey is shift A,
and that's what I'm going to do much more often.
And when I've created an auto layout
here, it's sort of like a parent frame
where it's going to just adjust the
spacing automatically for me.
So I'll just say, this is the to do list layer.
And then if I select the call Bob item, I
can press command D and it's going to
duplicate it in this list and it's going
to push down visit Dave just as much as
it needs to be pushed down
.
So now, this one can be call Alice, this
one can be email Bob, and again, if I
just press command D, then this one can
be gift for Carol.
Now, I can remove all of these items.
I don't need them anymore.
And I can just bring my auto layout list
up here.
Now, just a couple of things that changed.
One is with auto layouts because the
initial items had three pixels of spacing.
It just assumed that's what I want.
I actually initially had zero pixels of
spacing, so let's set that.
And then I did have different backgrounds.
So now the background is actually doubly
nested in the auto layout in the component.
To select a background layer directly, I
can just hold down Command and click.
And now I can see this has an opacity of 20%.
And this one, I'm going to re -add as
40%, this one as 60, and this one as 80.
And unfortunately, that's not something
that Figma knows how to automatically
update based on the number of items in
the list.
So that still has to be done manually,
but fair enough, I've still made things
easier with the auto layout.
And fun fact about auto layouts, they can
be nested.
So I could even select all three of these
things, press Shift -A again, and Figma
is going to guess that I want, you know,
on average, 55 pixels of space between them.
And then I can really quickly choose, do
I want more than that?
Less?
What's the deal?
But it's worth mentioning that the most
classic use of an auto layout is actually
for creating a button.
And this isn't something that's really
necessary for this design, but I'll show
you anyways, if I create a rectangle and
a text box, and the text box is
completely surrounded by the rectangle, I
can press shift a and get a nice little
button style right there, and then I can
go and, you know, change that rectangle
exactly how I would maybe give it four
pixels of border radius to be consistent
with the checkbox, maybe
give it a white background to be
consistent with some of the other stuff
and less opacity.
Oops, here's what's happening.
I'm changing the layer opacity.
And so it's changing the text as part of it.
I actually want to change the fill
opacity, something like this.
And with my auto layout, I have the
ability to update the horizontal padding,
that's the space around the sides, as
well as the vertical, and so on.
And so if I wanted this to look more like
a button, I could do that, but I'm
actually going to keep the circle for now.
It's just worth knowing that auto layout
is a very quick way to create buttons, in
addition to helping with the formatting
of lists.
Now, this design is looking pretty good,
so maybe I might want to just kind of
double -check that.
One thing I'll do, especially if I'm
designing a larger desktop screen, is I
will do Command -Shift -Backslash, and
that'll hide the layer list, and Command
-Backslash hides all the other UI.
This gives me a little bit more space to
just make sure my design looks exactly as
I've intended.
Like I said, I always do Shift -2, Shift
-0, to view at 100%.
And that's very important if you're
designing a desktop app on your desktop.
But for mobile app, what's even more
important is actually using the Figma
mobile app and just bringing up the
design on your phone.
So that's not something that's easy to
put in this video.
So I'll show you one of the next best
things, which is to just go to this
little play button here, present, and
that's going to bring up a one screen prototype.
But it's going to show our design in the
little outline of a phone, which just
kind of gives you a sense of how it appears.
And this is useful because I can see that
this little bar right here means, man,
maybe I should push my status bar down
just a tad, right?
And oops, because it's an auto layout,
that's actually much harder.
So what I'm going to do is remove the
auto layout with Command -Shift -G.
That's ungrouping all sorts of parent elements.
And I'll just move that down a touch.
And this thing should update instantaneously.
So I have the ability to update and then
view here.
And as we'll cover in a future lesson,
you can even set things such that if you
click, they interact and they can go
between screens as part of this presented prototype.
But if you have a design that you're
happy with, Then the question is now what?
And the most common thing that I find
myself doing is going to share and then
going to copy link here.
Now, if you do that, you want to make
sure that anyone with the link can at
least view.
They don't have to be an editor or else
Figma might start charging you, but you
want to make sure that everyone with the
link can view.
It's also fairly easy to do that just by
pressing command L and that's going to
copy the page if you don't have anything selected.
But I also like if I'm trying to direct a
client to a specific part of the design,
select that frame and then press command
L and it says frame link copied to Clipboard.
So they'll open that up and their browser
will be centered exactly on this design.
They won't even have to log in or anything.
They won't have to download the app, they
won't have to do anything fancy, they'll
just see your design and then they'll be
able to use comments, which you can
access by clicking here or pressing C and
they'll be able to say, Hey, it's not
January or whatever feedback they need to
give you.
Now, the other thing that you will most
often do to kind of finish up a design is
export it in some way or another.
And this can work in a couple different
ways because you can choose different
sizes and you can also choose different
file formats.
Now, the file formats are probably the
easiest to talk about.
A PNG is the most common way to export a design.
You could do JPEG too.
It's sometimes a smaller file size, but
it's also sometimes a little bit blurrier
and not quite as crisp.
So PNG is really usually fine for a design.
If you're exporting an icon or a logo or
something vector where someone can
scroll, where someone can zoom as far as
they want in on it and it doesn't get
blurry, then you almost certainly want to
be exporting an SVG.
And so if you choose SVG, the sizing
becomes irrelevant because it's scalable.
It can be zoomed in on as much as you want.
The fourth option is PDF.
And that's really only for if you're,
let's say, creating a poster or a slide
deck or something like that, which I've
done, but it's not really something we're
going to worry about directly in this course.
Now, as far as the sizing options go
here, 1x is the most common one that you
want to do.
It means that the image, when I'm at a
hundred percent zoom, it means that image
that it exports will be this size by default.
If I do two X, then the image will
actually be twice as large.
And so someone will need to zoom to 50 %
opacity, so someone will need to zoom to
50 % zoom to see it as you intended.
If you're posting an image on the student
community, please export at one X and
generally, I think that's the best size
to send to someone.
All right, folks, and that wraps it up
for an introduction to Figma.
So if you want more information on the
app, take a look at the resources below.
But other than that, there's no homework,
and we'll see you in the next video.